Holy Name Athletic Club records 1959-1997 CPAA 90-02
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Holy Name Athletic Club records
1959-1997
Holy Name Athletic Club
CPAA 90-02
8 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Holy Name Athletic Club (HNAC) was established in 1925 by members of the Polish American community in Stamford, Connecticut. HNAC had strong ties with the local Polish American parish, Holy Name of Jesus church. The Club received support from the parish and supported many charitable events at the church. The club organized athletic and social events to promote and to preserve activities and customs of Polonia. Material in the collection illustrates activities and membership in the Club for several decades. It includes also photographs from various sporting and social events.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Holy Name Athletic Club was organized in 1925 by the Rev. Stanislaus Nalewajk, a priest from the Holy Name of Jesus church and by Alexander J. Koproski, of Stamford, Connecticut together with fifteen others of Polish origin. The main purpose of the club was to promote athletic events, to participate in such events and also to foster and preserve the spirit and customs of Polish Americans. The club was always associated with the parish and members made many offerings to the church causes. From the very beginning the children from the parish school were invited for the annual Christmas party and this tradition is being continued till today. The club had very active and successful baseball team and the first team was established already in 1925 and participated in competitions that very year.
The club was well recognized as an outstanding athletic group in the state and at some point had over 400 members. Club members had to be of Polish origin or married to someone of Polish origin. Club constitution emphasized catholic values and strong support to catholic traditions. Club members wanted to embraces their values and to HNAC continues their activities till today.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Holy Name Athletic Club collection covers years 1959-1997. Collection contains financial statements, annual reports, board meeting minutes, correspondence, by-laws, membership information and yearly activities.
The collection is open for research.
Records of the Club were donated by Alexander Koproski in 1990 and second part was donated in 1997.
Search Terms
Holy Name Athletic Club -- Stamford -- Connecticut.; Polish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Polish Americans -- Stamford -- Connecticut.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Minutes.; Clippings.
Related Material
For related material see the following collections:
Alexander R. Koproski collection, CPAA 87-07
Arrangement
Material in the collection is arranged in three series. Foldres witin each series are in chronological order:
Series I Financial records and related papers.
Series II Board of Directors records and membership.
Series III Correspondence.
Series IV Club activities.
Series V General - insurance, renovations, lease.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Series I: Financial records and related papers., 1959-1997
  - HNAC records of financial secretary,[4 alphabetically arranged binders]., 1895-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - HNAC Financial statements., October, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - HNAC Financial statements., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - HNAC Annual reports., 1981-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - HNAC Monthly reports., 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - HNAC Monthly reports., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - HNAC Monthly reports., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - HNAC Monthly reports., 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - HNAC MOnthly reports., 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - HNAC Monthly reports., 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - HNAC Monthly reports., 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - HNAC Monthly reports., 1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - HNAC Bank of Stamford., 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1996 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - HNAC Financial monthly reports., 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - HNAC Documents from Stamford Federal Savings and Loans., 1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - HNAC Dues., 1965-1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - HNAC Income tax forms., 1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - HNAC Income tax., 1973-1974, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - HNAC Net wage analysis., May 1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - HNAC Tax returns., 1984-1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - HNAC Tax returns., 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - HNAC Tax returns., 1991-1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - HNAC Tax returns., 1994-1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - HNAC Income and expences., December 1993 - November 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - HNAC Bank account at Chase Gateway., 1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - HNAC FDIC Loan., 1992 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - HNAC Bar income., 1996 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - HNAC Sports committee budget., 1979 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - HNAC Special meeting regarding financial situation and option to lease., 1992 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - HNAC By-laws changes to comply with IRS code., 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series II: Board of Directors records and membership.
  - HNAC By-Laws., 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - HNAC Suggested by-laws revisions., 1979-1980, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - HNAC Constitution and by-laws., [1980?] (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - HNAC Annual meetings., 1972-1988, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1991 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1992 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1993 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1994 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1995 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - HNAC Board of Directors., 1996 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - HNAC Roaster., 1969, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - HNAC officers., 1973-1988 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - HNAC Canceled membership file., 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - HNAC membership information., 1966-1981 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - HNAC membership committee., 1981-1982, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - HNAC Roaster and membership list., 1992, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - HNAC membership lists., 1996 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - HNAC survey of members in support of club's activities., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - HNAC survey of members on the future of the club., 1997 (Box 6, Folder 27A)
  - HNAC Past presidents and life members., 1973-1983 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - HNAC Questionnare for members., 1972 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - HNAC Women's Auxilliary membership list., 1993 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - HNAC Application for membership., 1965-1975 (Box 7)
- Series III: Correspondence.
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1984-1987 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1988 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1991 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1992 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1993 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1994 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1995 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - HNAC Correspondence., 1996 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - HNAC Stationary. (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - HNAC Re-dedication of the club - related correspondence., May 21, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - HNAC Newsletter., 1973-1977 (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Series IV: Club activities.
  - HNAC Communion Breakfast., 1979-1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - HNAC Communion Breakfast (includes photographs)., 1983-1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - HNAC Communion Breakfast (includes photographs)., 1991 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - HNAC Communion Breakfast., 1992 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - HNAC Communion Breakfast (includes photographs)., 1993 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - HNAC Communion Breakfast., 1994 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - HNAC Communion Breakfast., 1995 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - HNAC Communion Breakfast., 1996 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - HNAC Polish Cultural Committee., 1973 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - HNAC Participation in sports competition., 1972-1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - HNAC Clippings related to sport activities and events., 1986-1991 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - HNAC Sports and Social Committee., 1983-1995 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - HNAC Softball team., 1991 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - HNAC Olimpia Polish soccer team in Stamford., 1994 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - HNAC Clippings related to sports events involving Polish-Americans., 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - HNAC Sports history of Stamford, clippings., 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - HNAC Anniversary Dinner Dance., 1966-1974 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - HNAC Memorial Day Dance 50th Anniversary., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - HNAC Harvest Festival., 1986-1990 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - HNAC Harvest Festival., 1992-1994 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - HNAC Children's Christmas party., 1983-1994 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - HNAC Reports from various cultural and social events., 1969-1979 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - HNAC New Year's Eve celebration., 1989-1996 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - HNAC Christmas party for children., 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - HNAC Adults Christmas Party., 1981-1983, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - HNAC Raffle fundriser., 1974-1989 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - HNAC Raffle permit., 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - HNAC English language classes., 1992 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - HNAC English language classes., 1992 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - HNAC English language classes., 1993 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - HNAC English language classes., 1994 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - HNAC Annual picnics., 1971-1979 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - HNAC Annual picnics., 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - HNAC Annual picnics., 1985-1989 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - HNAC Bulk mail permit., 1978-1980 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - HNAC Newsclippings., 1972-1978 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - HNAC Miscellaneous publicity., 1992 (Box 7, Folder 37)
- Series V: General - insurance, renovations, leases, etc.
  - HNAC Insurance., 1995-1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - HNAC Insurance policies., 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - HNAC Atlantic street traffic change., 1995 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - HNAC Permittee file., 1992-1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - HNAC Liquor permitt., 1976-1981 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - HNAC Emploees, rules, etc., 1983-1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - HNAC Building and equipment, etc., 1978-1980 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - HNAC Renovation projects., 1980 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - HNAC Main building and appartment renovations., 1990 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - HNAC air and cooling system renovation., 1992 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - HNAC Basement renovation., 1994 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - HNAC Parking income., 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - HNAC Main hall rental., 1990's (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - HNAC Kitchen lease., 1982-1988 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - HNAC Kitchen lease., 1989-1992 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - HNAC Lease agreements with Pitney-Bowes, Inc., 1973-1979 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - HNAC Lease agreement with Pitney-Bowes, Inc., 1982-1990 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - HNAC Lease agreement with Pitney Bowes, Inc.., 1990-1997 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - HNAC Postal Workers Union lease agreement., 1980-1987 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - HNAC photographs: Holy Name Athletic Club baseball team (ca 1930); Stanislaw Hausner (aviator) (June 1932; HNAC Board members 46th anniversary of the Club (1971). (Box 9, Folder flat box)